Guide to the Tomas Venclova Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tomas Venclova papers
1909-2005
1959-2005
GEN MSS 714
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
30.71
(36 boxes) + 2 rolls, 1 broadside folder, and electronic files
The Tomas Venclova Papers document the life and work of Lithuanian poet, scholar and professor Tomas Venclova. Correspondence documents Venclova's relationships with Lithuanian and Soviet literary figures and political dissidents, including letters from Joseph Brodsky and Czesław Miłosz. Venclova's personal life and family relationships are also documented in the correspondence. Venclova's work as a poet, scholar, and translator is documented in drafts of writings that include holograph drafts of poetry. His work as a human rights activist is documented in the subject files, which include files on Adam Michnik and Liudmila Alekseeva. Photographs include personal and family photographs as well as photographs of conferences, readings and other professional travel. Audiovisual material includes recordings of poetry readings and lectures. Printed material includes reviews of Venclova's works and articles about Lithuanian politics and culture in the 1990s. Electronic files consist chiefly of e-mail. Other papers include personal documents, awards and honorary degrees.
Venclova, Tomas, 1937-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Tomas Venclova on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004, and gift of Tomas Venclova, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 33 (correspondence): Restricted until 2034 November 1. Box 34 (audiovisual material): Restricted until 2054 September 24. Box 35 (diaries): restricted until 2019 September 24. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 36: (computer disk): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files are available. Consult Access Services for further information.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the audiovisual material have been digitally reformatted. Use copies may be requested. Consult Beinecke Access Services for further information.
Tomas Venclova, 1937-
Tomas Andrious Venclova, poet, scholar and Professor of Slavic Literature at Yale University, was born on September 11, 1937 in Klaipėda, Lithuania. Active in the Soviet dissident movement, he was forced to emigrate in 1977. He came to the United States, where he obtained temporary positions at the University of California and Ohio University before accepting a position at Yale University in 1980. In the United States, Venclova continued to advocate actively on behalf of dissidents and writers in the Sovet Bloc.
Venclova's major writings include: Kalbos ženklas: eilėraščiai (1972), Neustoichivoe ravnovesie: Vosem' russkikh poeticheskikh tekstov (1986) Tankėjanti šviesa (1990), and Aleksander Wat: Life and art of an iconoclast (1996). He also published several volumes of Lithuanian translations, including the poetry of Anna Akhmatova, Joseph Brodsky and Czesław Miłosz.
Scope and Contents
The Tomas Venclova Papers document the life and work of Lithuanian poet, scholar and professor Tomas Venclova. Correspondence documents Venclova's relationships with Lithuanian and Soviet literary figures and political dissidents, including letters from Joseph Brodsky and Czesław Miłosz. Venclova's personal life and family relationships are also documented in the correspondence. Venclova's work as a poet, scholar, and translator is documented in drafts of writings that include holograph drafts of poetry. His work as a human rights activist is documented in the subject files, which include files on Adam Michnik and Liudmila Alekseeva. Photographs include personal and family photographs as well as photographs of conferences, readings and other professional travel. Audiovisual material includes recordings of poetry readings and lectures. Printed material includes reviews of Venclova's works and articles about Lithuanian politics and culture in the 1990s. Electronic files consist chiefly of e-mail. Other papers include personal documents, awards and honorary degrees.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series: I. Correspondence, circa 1972-2003. II. Writings, circa 1946-2004. III. Subject files and Ephemera, 1977-2004. IV. Photographs, circa 1909-2004. V. Audiovisual Material, 1971-2004. VI. Printed Material, circa 1975-2003. VII. Electronic files, 1997-2004. VIII. Other Papers, 1976-2004.
Authors, Lithuanian -- 20th Century; Poets, Lithuanian -- 20th Century; Lithuanian literature -- 20th Century; Lithuanian poetry -- 20th Century; Dissenters -- Soviet Union; Emigration and immigration; Lithuania -- Politics and government; Audiovisual materials; Audiotapes; Videotapes; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs; Electronic documents; Alekseeva, Li︠u︡dmila, 1927-; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996; Venclova, Tomas, 1937-; Michnik, Adam, 1946-; Miłosz, Czesław, 1911-2004
- Correspondence, circa 1972-2003; Series I
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also: Series VII, Electronic Files
  - "A" General Correspondence, 5 (Box 1)
  - "B" General Correspondence, 7 (Box 1)
  - "C" General Correspondence, 3 (Box 1)
  - "D" General Correspondence, 4 (Box 1)
  - "E" General Correspondence, 3 (Box 1)
  - "F" General Correspondence, 4 (Box 1)
  - "G" General Correspondence, 6 (Box 1)
  - "H" General Correspondence, 4 (Box 1)
  - "I-J" General Correspondence, 5 (Box 1)
  - "K" General Correspondence, 7 (Box 2)
  - "L" General Correspondence, 5 (Box 2)
  - "M" General Correspondence, 8 (Box 2)
  - "N" General Correspondence, 4 (Box 2)
  - "O" General Correspondence, 4 (Box 2)
  - "P-Q" General Correspondence, 4 (Box 2)
  - "R" General Correspondence, 5 (Box 3)
  - "S" General Correspondence, 7 (Box 3)
  - "T" General Correspondence, 6 (Box 3)
  - "U-V" General Correspondence, 6 (Box 3)
  - "W" General Correspondence, 5 (Box 3)
  - "X-Z" General Correspondence, 3 (Box 3)
  - Baltušytė, Rita, 1980-1988 (Box 4)
  - Barańczak, Stanisław, 1984-2001; 2 (Box 4)
  - Błoński, Jan, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Bojtár, Endre, 1978-1990 (Box 4)
  - Bradūnas, Kazys, 1977-1991 (Box 4)
  - Brodsky, Joseph, outgoing (copies), undated (Box 4)
  - Chertkov, Leonid, 1978-1984 (Box 4)
  - Etkind, Efim, 1978-1997 (Box 4)
  - Finkel'shtein, Eitan, 1980-2003; 2 (Box 4)
  - Gaučys, Povilas, 1983-1990 (Box 4)
  - Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1977-1992 (Box 4)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1998-2002 (Box 4)
  - Ivask, Ivar, 1977-1986 (Box 4)
  - Kaplanas, I., 1980-1985 (Box 4)
  - Katilius, Ramunas, 1977-1993 (Box 4)
  - Kavolis, Vytautas, 1977-1994 (Box 4)
  - Keblys, Kęstutis, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
  - Kline, George, incoming and outgoing (including copies), 1976-2001; 2 (Box 4)
  - Landsbergis, Algirdas, 1979-2002 (Box 4)
  - Lankauskas, Romualdas and Regina, 1981-1990 (Box 4)
  - Lukauskaitė-Poškienė, Ona, 1977-1980 (Box 4)
  - Miłosz, Czesław, 1983-1999 (Box 4)
  - New Republic, 1986-1998 (Box 4)
  - Polukhina, Valentina, 1987-1997; 1 (Box 4)
  - Raila, Bronys, 1977-1987 (Box 4)
  - Rekašius, Zenonas, 1977-1993 (Box 4)
  - Shtromas, Violeta and Alexander, 1980-1994; 2 (Box 4)
  - Šilbajoris, Rimvydas, 1977-1994 (Box 4)
  - Šimkutė, Lidija, 1977-1988 (Box 4)
  - Skrupskelytė, Viktorija, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Skuodis, Vytautas, 1988-1991 (Box 4)
  - Slavinas, Julius, 1984-1996 (Box 4)
  - Szymborska, Wisława, 2001-2003 (Box 4)
  - Temkina, Marina, 1986-2001 (Box 4)
  - Torunczyk, Barbara, 1987-2000; 3 (Box 4)
  - Trauberg, Natalia, 1978-1990, undated; 4 (Box 5)
  - Vepstas, Henrietta, 1977-1990 (Box 5)
  - Vėžys, Gintautas, 1978-1989 (Box 5)
  - Venclova, Maria, including photographs, 1978-1997, undated; 5 (Box 5)
  - Venclova, Maria and Andrei, 1985-2002, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Venclovienė, Eliza and other family members, incoming and outgoing (including copies), 1972-1997; 4 (Box 5)
  - Woroszylski, Wiktor, 1978-2002 (Box 5)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1977-2001; 3 (Box 5)
  - Unsorted correspondence, "Letters from eminent writers, scholars, dissidents and political figures", 3 (Box 5)
- Writings, circa 1946-2004; Series II
  - "My poetry," typescript (copies), undated; 2 (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes translations from Lithuanian to English by Diana Senechal.
  - Poetry, English translations by Diana Senechal, printouts (including copies), undated (Box 6)
  - Poetry, including translations into English by Venclova and Diana Senechal, typescript (copies), undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Shakespeare's The Tempest, Lithuanian translation by Venclova, typescript carbon and printout, undated (Box 6)
  - Translations of Venclova's poetry into Spanish, Polish, and English, printouts (including copies), undated (Box 6)
  - Translations of Venclova's poetry into Polish, by Stanisław Barańczak, printout and printed version (copies), undated (Box 6)
  - "My poetry," holograph and printouts, undated; 4 (Box 6)
  - Poems, final corrected versions, printed version (copy), 1999; 2 (Box 6)
  - Poems, including translations into various languages, typescripts and printed versions (copies), undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Poems, translations into various languages, printed versions (including copies), 1980-2002, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Poems, translations into Russian, English and German by Kulle, Mil', Gandel'sman, Senechal, Vaisnis and Fieguth, printouts and printed versions (copies), undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - Rozmówa w zimie, proof, corrected (copy), circa 1989 (Box 7)
  - New Poems, printouts (including copies), undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - Poems, translations into Polish, English and Russian, typescripts, printouts, proofs and printed versions (including copies), undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - Tomas Venclova's work in Lithuanian, holograph, typescript and printed material (including copies), undated; 4 (Box 7)
  - Aleksander Wat: Life and art of an iconoclast, notes and drafts, circa 1990-1996; 2 (Box 7)
  - Aleksander Wat: Life and art of an iconoclast, notes and drafts, circa 1990-1996; 2 (Box 7)
  - Aleksander Wat: Life and art of an iconoclast, draft, printout, circa 1996; 10 (Box 8)
  - Stat'i o Brodskom, proof, corrected, circa 2005 (Box 8)
  - Childhood drawings and poems by Tomas Venclova, 1946? (Box 8)
  - "Some of my work before emigration," notes and drafts, before 1977 (Box 8)
    Includes material for lectures on Akhmatova, Mandel'shtam and applied linguistics
  - Notes on Anna Akhmatova, including a memoir of a meeting with her, holograph, typescript and printout, 1995, undated (Box 8)
  - Vilniaus asmenybės ( Vilnius personalities ), printout, 2004; 4 (Box 8)
  - Tomas Venclova's work in Polish, printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1977-2004, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Non-scholarly work in Russian, typescripts, printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1978-2000, undated; 3 (Box 9)
  - Scholarly work in Russian, typescripts, printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1984-1985, undated; 4 (Box 9)
  - Non-scholarly work in English, holograph, typescripts, printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1983-2003, undated; 4 (Box 9)
  - Scholarly work in English, typescripts, printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1980-2002, undated; 4 (Box 9)
  - Material for Venclova's first dissertation on Jurgis Baltrushaitis, holograph, typescript and printed material (including copies), 1970s (Box 10)
  - Tomas Venclova's work and reviews of his work in French, Spanish, Italian, German, etc., printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1978-1996, undated (Box 10)
  - Reviews of Tomas Venclova's work, printouts and printed versions (including copies), 1979-2004, undated; 4 (Box 10)
  - Neustoichivoe ravnovesie: Vosem' russkikh poeticheskikh tekstov, proof, corrected (copy), circa 1986 (Box 10)
  - Essays and notes by Tomas Venclova, holograph, undated (Box 10)
  - Drafts of writings (poetry and prose), holograph and typescript, 2004, undated; 2 (Box 10)
  - Two poems by 8-year-old Tomas Venclova, holograph, 1945 (Box 10)
- Subject files and Ephemera, 1977-2004; Series III
  - Brodsky, Joseph, including letters to Venclova, notes and manuscript poems by Brodsky, 1977-1996; 4 (Box 10)
  - Brodsky, Joseph, newspaper and magazine articles, 1996-2003; 2 (Box 10)
  - Brodsky, Joseph, Czesław Miłosz and Wisława Szymborska, ephemera, 1996-2004 (Box 10)
  - Miłosz, Czesław, including correspondence and copies of Szukanie ojczyzny by Miłosz, 1982-2000; 3 (Box 10)
  - Vilnius, including a draft of "Vilnius/Wilno/Vilna" (corrected printout) and printed material (including copies), 1990, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Keleras, Julius, including poems in Lithuanian and English translations, printout (copy), undated (Box 11)
  - Rannit, Aleksis, offprints and printed writings (including copies), 1978-1982, undated (Box 11)
  - Rannit, Aleksis, clippings and copies of printed writings, 1977-1985, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Human rights movement, including correspondence and reports, 1977-1987, undated (Box 11)
  - Human rights movement, correspondence and printed material, 1977-1983; 3 (Box 11)
  - Michnik, Adam, including copies of his letters to Barbara Toruńczyk, undated (Box 11)
  - Lithuanian independence movement, newspaper clippings, 1988-1991 (Box 11)
  - Venclova family, printed material and photographs (including copies), 1981-1998, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Shtromas, Alexander, offprints, printout and proof, 1986-1989 (Box 11)
  - Venclova, Andrei and Maria, including correspondence and clippings, 1994-2002 (Box 11)
  - Lithuanian dissidents and other writers (including Mark Strand, Gennady Aigi, Marina Temkina, Ory Bernstein and Natanlia Gorbanevskaia), correspondence, writings and clippings, 1980-2003, undated; 3 (Box 11)
  - Alekseeva, Liudmila, including copies of third-party correspondence, 1979-1989, undated (Box 11)
  - Venclova, Tomas, articles in Russian about him, 1977-2002 (Box 11)
  - Ephemera in French, including invitations and announcements, 1989-1992, undated (Box 11)
  - Ephemera and correspondence in German, 1979-2000 (Box 11)
  - Ephemera and correspondence in Spanish, 1983-1999, undated (Box 11)
  - Ephemera in Italian, Dutch, German, Arabic, Chinese, Japanese and Belorussian, 1984-2003, undated (Box 11)
  - Ephemera and clippings relating to friends, 1978-2003; 3 (Box 12)
  - Ephemera and printed material, chiefly from conferences and events, 1983-1993, undated; 7 (Box 12)
  - Ephemera, 10 (Box 12)
  - Ephemera, announcements for Tomas Venclova's readings, 1976-2004, undated
- Photographs, circa 1909-2004; Series IV
  - Tomas Venclova with Howard Bloom, 2002 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Czesław Miłosz, 1980-2003; 2 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Adam Michnik, 1993-2001 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Alexander and Violeta Shtromas, 1980-1988 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Lithuanian writers and friends, 1977-2002 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with various friends, 1993-2003 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Lithuanian celebrities, 1983-2002 (Box 13)
  - Early photographs of Tomas Venclova, 1937-1990 (Box 13)
  - Memorials for Boris Pasternak, Anna Akhmatova, Joseph Brodsky, and Czesław Miłosz, 1995-2004 (Box 13)
  - Snapshots of Tomas Venclova, 1987-2004 (Box 13)
  - Professional portraits of Tomas Venclova, 1978-2001 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova at the Anna Akhmatova Museum, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova in Vilnius, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Maria Venclova, 1970s (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova in Sejny and Vilnius, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Houses and apartments, 1980-2004, undated (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova with Russian and Polish celebreties, 1991-2002 (Box 13)
  - Tomas Venclova at meetings, celebrations and public occasions, 1977-2004; 2 (Box 13)
  - Joseph Brodsky, 1987-1993 (Box 13a)
  - Šiauliai Drama Theater, 1970s (Box 13a)
  - Unsorted photographs, 1978-1988 (Box 13a)
  - Photographs of friends (Joseph Brodsky, Ramunas Katilius, Andrei Sergeev, V. Bykovski), 1970s, undated (Box 13a)
  - Various friends and relatives, 1960s-2002 (Box 13a)
  - Tomas Venclova in St. Petersburg, 2002 (Box 13a)
  - Portraits and document photographs, 1951-2001; 2 (Box 13a)
  - Travels, 1995-2003; 24 (Box 14)
  - Tomas Venclova in Lithuania, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Summer school in Warsaw, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Book signing in Warsaw, 1991 (Box 14)
  - Tomas Venclova receiving an award in Vilnius, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Tomas Venclova with Leszek Kołakowski, undated (Box 14)
  - Poetry reading in Kiel, Germany, 2003 (Box 14)
  - Memorial stone for Henkus Hapenčkus, undated (Box 14)
  - Snapshots of Tomas Venclova, 1995-2001 (Box 14)
  - Family photographs, circa 1909-1990, undated; 2 (Box 14)
  - Tomas Venclova as a child, circa 1937-1940 (Box 14)
  - Unsorted photographs, 1972-2002; 5 (Box 14)
  - Tomas Venclova with his daughter Maria and with N. Ogai, circa 1975-1992
- Audiovisual Material, 1971-2004; Series V
  Recordings of conversations with Joseph Brodsky are stored in Restricted Material.
  - "Litwa Tomasza Venclovy", 1994; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Tomas Venclova's poetry in Polish, 1992; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Tomas Venclova's autobiography read by the author, 1998; (2 audio cassettes) (Box 15)
  - Tomas Venclova reads his poetry in Russian, 1997; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Tomas Venclova's interview at Radio Vilnius in Lithuanian, circa 1997; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Blank cassette labeled as a lecture at Brown University on Akhmatova's Sreten'e, 2003; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Tomas Venclova's lecture on the dissident movement at Brown University, 2003 April 12; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Interview with Kultur in German, 2003 April 25; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Tomas Venclova reading poetry in Lithuanian, 2003; (2 audio cassettes) (Box 15)
  - Radio interview in Krakow, 1993 July 2; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - "Lithuania", 1990 April 17; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - "Interview", undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Interview with Norwegian radio, 1999; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Polish program about Tomas Venclova, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Interview with Tomas Venclova, 1994 February; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - "Joseph Brodsky Etcetera Etcetera", undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 15)
  - Joseph Brodsky interview with Tomas Venclova, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Tomas Venclova reads his diary about his trip to India, 2003; (2 audio cassettes) (Box 16)
  - Piotr Brania performs songs based on the poetry of Joseph Brodsky and Tomas Venclova, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Sunday feature: Milosz's ABC, 2001; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - The poet's voice: Czeslaw Milosz (WNYC), undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Viktor Krivulin and Regina Derieva read Tomas Venclova's poetry, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Interview with Natan Sharanskii, IUrii Orlov and Tomas Venclova, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Conversation with Andrzej Wat, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Interview with Tatiana Milovidova, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Conversation with Polkovnik and Wardak, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - The poetry of Aleksandr Kushner, read by Era Korobova, undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Interview with Andrei Voznesenskii (MacNeil-Lehrer Hour), 1988 April 8; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - "Boris Mansurov", undated; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - "Sindrom ZHirinovskogo", 1994 April; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Kaupas, Julius, Daktaras Kripštukas pragare, 1992; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Vilniaus geto dainos, 2001; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Radioshow Unplugged, "Dieve Mano!", 1995; (1 audio cassette) (Box 16)
  - Valatkos Pareiskimas, undated; (1 audio reel) (Box 17)
  - Głosy Poetów, 1997; (2 audio cassettes) (Box 17)
  - Various commercial compact discs, 1996-2002, undated; (6 compact discs) (Box 17)
  - German translations of Tomas Venclova, read by Kurt Neumann, undated; (1 compact disc) (Box 17)
  - Einstein forum, Potsdam, undated; (1 compact disc) (Box 17)
  - Witold Gombrowicz, directed by Andrzej Wolski, undated; (1 DVD) (Box 17)
  - Tomas Venclova, Club Poetique -- 58. Treffen, 2003?; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 18)
  - The poet & the piper, Seamus Heaney and Liam O'Flynn, 2003; (1 compact disc) (Box 18)
  - Pożegnanie poety, 2004; (1 DVD) (Box 19)
  - Interview with Tomas Venclova for Latvian television, 2004; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 19)
  - Charlie Rose: Durning/Guggenheim/Brodsky Tribute, 1996 March 19; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 19)
  - "The Wedding," filmed by J. Mekas, undated; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 19)
  - "Tomas Venclova entreviste en el 2/ Tomas Venclova C.4 Caracas l del 83", undated; (1 Betamax cassette) (Box 20)
    Folder description is transcribed from the cassette.
  - Masha in Vilnius/Interview with Tomas and Tania, 2001; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Moment in History / Bloody Sunday, 1990-1991; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Rebirth of a Nation, undated; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Anna Akhmatova, produced and directed by Jill Janows (WGBH), undated; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - A cat and a half, directed by A. Khrzhanovsky, 2002; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - "Tomas, Charlie Rose", 1996?; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Doroga v rai, Festival (1951) in Moscow, undated; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Joseph Brodsky, LTV, "Santarvės", 1997; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Lithuania 2000/ Dedication of the Brodsky memorial in Vilnius, (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Tomas Venclova in Vilnius/ VDU in Kaunas and in New Haven, undated; (1 VHS cassette) (Box 20)
  - Poland: World Slavic Congress/ Tomas Venclova visits Czesław Miłosz, 1998; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 21)
  - Venclova at home with Czesław Miłosz/ Conversation with Vasilii Rusich, 1997-1998; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 21)
  - California conference on Czesław Miłosz, 1998; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 21)
  - Dedication of a memorial to Joseph Brodsky in Vilnius (Grass, Szymborska, Miłosz, Venclova), 2000; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 21)
  - 60th birthday of Tomas Venclova: Celebrations and meetings in various places, 1997; (4 mini VHS cassettes) (Box 21)
  - Tomas Venclova receiving a Polish literary prize for his book on Aleksander Wat, New York, 1996; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 21)
  - Meeting with Polish scholars and poets, undated; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 21)
  - Family recordings, travels and friends, 1999-2000; (4 mini VHS cassettes) (Box 22)
  - In Germany, Rügen Island and Lübenau, 1998; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 22)
  - Travels, 2000; (3 mini VHS cassettes) (Box 22)
  - Lecture at the Jewish Community Center in Woodbridge, CT/ Poetry in Russian, 1999; (1 mini VHS cassette) (Box 22)
  - Ne margi sakalėliai, by Virgilijus Noreika and Povilas Jaraminas, 1986
  - Kūrybos vakaras, by Antanas Venclova, 1971
- Printed Material, circa 1975-2003; Series VI
  - Newspaper clippings from non-Lithiuanian publications (including copies), 1977-1978 (Box 23)
  - Newspaper clippings about Venclova's emigration (including copies), 1975-1976 (Box 23)
  - English translations of Venclova's poetry by Audra Misiunas, typescript (copy), 1976 (Box 23)
  - Newspaper clippings in English (including copies), 1977-1978 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 2003; 3 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 2002; 2 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 2001; 2 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 2000; 2 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 1999 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 1998; 2 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 1997; 3 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1996; 3 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1995; 2 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1994 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1993; 3 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1992; 2 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1991; 2 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1991; 3 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1990; 4 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1989 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1988 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1980-1981 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1977 and earlier (Box 25)